SARANSH CHOPRA

🏶 saransh-cpp.github.io | 🗖 saransh0701@gmail.com | 🗖 saransh-cpp | 🗗 Saransh-cpp | 🗗 Blogs

About

Saransh is an engineering junior who, by day, works on his academic and professional commitments, and by night, develops and maintains Open-Source Software, which he believes are the key to reproducible and collaborative research.

He is passionate about Software Development, DevOps, Research Software Engineering, Machine Learning, Scientific Machine Learning, and Open-Source Research Software.

Education

Cluster Innovation Centre, University of Delhi

New Delhi, India

 ${\it Major: Information \ Technology \ and \ Mathematical \ Innovations}$

2020 - 2024

Minor: Computational Biology

CGPA 9.40

Research and Work Experience

FluxML, The Julia Programming Language

Remote

Technical Writer and Open-Source Developer [Funded by The Julia Programming Language] May 2022 – November 2022 Mr. Dhairya Gandhi (Julia Computing)

- Worked on FluxML, an ML ecosystem providing lightweight abstractions on top of Julia's native GPU and AD support.
- Fixed bugs and developed the infrastructure of numerous ML packages such as Flux.jl, NNlib.jl and Metalhead.jl.
- Wrote original Machine Learning/Deep Learning tutorials, documentation and API references for FluxML's ecosystem.

Institute for Research and Innovation in Software for High Energy Physics (IRIS-HEP), Princeton University

Remote

Research and Development Fellow [Funded by IRIS-HEP]

June 2022 - October 2022

Dr. Henry Schreiner (Princeton University / CERN) and Dr. Jim Pivarski (Princeton University)

- Prepared Vector, a Python library for constructing Just-In-Time compilable jagged Lorentz vectors, for v0.9.0, v0.10.0, and v1.0.0 (first major release).
- \circ Worked closely with CERN researchers to develop new API, fix bugs, and build infrastructures for the HEP ecosystem.
- The releases are currently being used by researchers at CERN, Princeton University, and other research institutes.

AiView New Delhi, India

Research and Development Engineer

September 2021 – December 2021

Mr. Geetansh Saxena and Mr. Chappa Sri Vinay

- o Developed end-to-end OCR and Object Detection libraries by wrapping existing software for visually impaired people.
- o Built a CI/CD pipeline and a REST API for ease of integration with any existing software using FastAPI and Heroku.
- Collected a dataset of human images and their distance from a point by building a stereovision camera.

PyBaMM (Python Battery Mathematical Modelling), NumFOCUS

Remote

Google Summer of Code Student Developer [Funded by Google]

May 2021 – August 2021

Prof. Ferran Brosa Planella (University of Warwick), Dr. Valentin Sulzer (Carnegie Melon University), Dr. Robert Timms (University of Oxford)

- Built an automated Twitter Bot capable of constructing Mathematical Simulations of Batteries, including but not limited to different battery models, parameter sets, chemistries, degradation modes, and experiments.
- o Developed a replying functionality to run Mathematical Simulations on command using Twitter API.
- Created a novel CI CD infrastructure and followed a micro-services-based architecture.

Open Source Research Software

PyBaMMNumFOCUS Steering Committee Member, Maintainer, and Core Developer - 450+ stars
PyBaMM (Python Battery Mathematical Modelling) solves physics-based electrochemical DAE models by using state-of-the-art
automatic differentiation and numerical solvers.

 $egin{array}{lll} egin{array}{lll} egin{array}{lll} egin{array}{lll} egin{array}{lll} Collaborator \ and \ Core \ Contributor \ - \ 45 + \ stars \end{array} \end{array}$

Vector is a Python 3.7+ library for 2D, 3D, and Lorentz vectors, especially arrays of vectors, to solve common physics problems in a NumPy-like way.

[SSP] S. Chopra, H. Schreiner, and J. Pivarski. Vector: vector classes and utilities. DOI: 10.5281/zenodo.5942082. URL: https://github.com/scikit-hep/vector.

Flux.jl

Member (FluxML) and Core Contributor - 3,700+ stars

Flux is an elegant approach to machine learning. It's a 100% pure-Julia stack, and provides lightweight abstractions on top of Julia's native GPU and AD support. Flux makes the easy things easy while remaining fully hackable.

BattBot

Member (pybamm-team), Maintainer, and Core Developer - 10+ stars

An automated Twitter Bot that Tweets random Battery Mathematical Modeling Simulations and replies to the requested Battery Simulations.

liionpack

Member (pybamm-team), Maintainer, and Core Developer - 30+ stars

liionpack takes a 1D PyBaMM model and makes it into a pack. You can either specify the configuration e.g. 16 cells in parallel and 2 in series (16p2s) or load a netlist.

Other notable contributions

- Zarr: An implementation of chunked, compressed, N-dimensional arrays for Python. 1,000+ stars Migrated Zarr's build and packaging infrastructure to a pyproject.toml based configuration.
- **DeepXDE**: DeepXDE is a library for scientific machine learning 1,200+ stars Implemented utility functions and improved the existing examples on solving partial differential PDEs using PINNs.
- \circ Colour: Colour Science for Python 1,500+ stars Implemented the conversion between RGB and HCL colourspaces, along with tests and documentation.
- Scikit-HEP ecosystem: High Energy Physics in Python

 Fixed minor bugs in awkward and hist, added support for coverage in cookie, and wrote new developer pages.
- Scikits.odes: Offers extra ODE/DAE solvers; an extension to ones available in SciPy 100+ stars

 Debugged and fixed their build (which was failing because of setuptools) and removed support for Python 2.7-3.6.

Posters and Presentations

- [SSP22a] S. Chopra, H. Schreiner, and J. Pivarski. Compiling Awkward Lorentz vectors with Numba. 21st International Workshop on Advanced Computing and Analysis Techniques in Physics Research (ACAT). Poster (upcoming). Oct. 2022. URL: https://indi.to/45Kzq.
- [SSP22b] S. Chopra, H. Schreiner, and J. Pivarski. Constructing HEP vectors and analyzing HEP data using Vector. 5th International Workshop on Python in High Energy Physics (PyHEP). Presentation. Oct. 2022. DOI: https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7081003. URL: https://indi.to/bPmMc.
- [S C22a] S. Chopra. Code coverage through unit tests running in sub-processes/threads: Locally and automated on GitHub. 10th Annual Conference on Python Asia-Pacific (PyCon APAC). Presentation. Sept. 2022. URL: https://tw.pycon.org/2022/en-us/conference/talk/243.
- [S C22b] S. Chopra. Code coverage through unit tests running in sub-processes/threads: Locally and automated on GitHub. 21st Annual Conference On Python Europe (EuroPython). Presentation. July 2022. URL: https://ep2022.europython.eu/session/code-coverage-through-unit-tests-running-in-sub-processes-threads-locally-and-automated-on-github.

Grants, Prizes and Achievements

• PyCon Acia-Pacific (APAC)'s grant to lead a talk virtually (NT\$3,600)

July 2022

• Shubhra Kar Linux Foundation Training Scholarship (500 recipients worldwide) for contributions to open-source research software (\$695)

June 2022

• EuroPython's travel grant to lead a talk in-person (£460)

June 2022

• PyCon Italia's travel grant to lead a workshop in-person (£400 + lodging support)

April 2022

• Faraday Institution's Collaboration Award for contributions to the PyBaMM ecosystem

November 2021

• Won the **Elastic hackathon** (out of 2500+ registrations) with a Flutter-Node-Google Cloud-ELK (Elasticsearch, Logstash, Kibana) based application

May 2021

• Discovered an asteroid having a fixed orbit around Sun by analysing the data

August 2016

Pan-STARRS observatory

Projects

releaseup [NLP, Text summarisation, spaCy, Scikit-learn, TF-IDF, Python library]

 $September\ 2022$

- Release up uses an extractive approach for generating release notes from comments and docstrings added b/w two git tags.
- The Python library has 400+ installs on PyPI, 5+ stars on GitHub, and follows best development practices.

- OCRed provides clever, simple, and intuitive wrapper functionalities for OCRing specific textual materials.
- The Python library has 2,900+ installs on PyPI, 10+ stars on GitHub, and follows best development practices.

ForMente [NLP, Flutter, Dart, FastAPI, Python, Firebase, Firestore, Heroku, GitHub Actions]

June 2022

- Using Natural Language Processing, ForMente lets you diagnose your feelings in the form of a secure personal diary.
- The NLP model is deployed on Heroku using FastAPI, and the app uses Firebase and Firestore as its backend.

SceneNet [Transfer Learning, VGG19, CNNs, Python, Flutter, Dart, FastAPI, Heroku]

December 2021

- Scenery detection through an Android application achieved by training VGG-19 on 10,000+ images belonging to 67 categories.
- Achieved 96% training accuracy, 64% cross-validation accuracy, and developed a standalone public API for the model.

PopItUp [Android, Kotlin, Firebase, Firestore, Google Sceneform SDK, Google ARCore SDK]

August 2021

- An Augmented Reality shooting game developed in native android by manually adding and editing the Sceneform SDK.
- Developed a live leaderboard using the FirestoreRecyclerView and Firestore.

MemeTastic [Flutter, Dart, NodeJS, Elasticsearch, Kibana, CI/CD, Google Cloud, Reddit API, Ngram Analyser] May 2021

- Developed and deployed a backend service to ingest the latest meme data into Google Cloud hosted Elasticsearch.
- o Created a frontend with a clean UI to fetch this data, providing an auto-complete feature to search any meme.

Position of Responsibilities, Volunteering, and Mentoring

• Member of PyBaMM's NumFOCUS steering committee.

Present

• Member of FluxML's GitHub organisation.

Present

• **Vector**'s collaborator on GitHub.

Present

• Invited to mentor a hackashop at the **PyHEP workshop**.

September 2022

• Mentored students under PyBaMM, NumFOCUS for Google Summer of Code 2022.

May 2022

• Mentored 10+ students under Codepeak 2021 on open-source application development.

December 2021

Relevant Skills

Languages: Python (proficient) | Julia (proficient) | Dart (proficient) | C/C++ | Java | JavaScript

Frameworks/Libraries: Tensorflow | PyTorch | FluxML-Ecosystem | PyData-Ecosystem | SciML-Ecosystem | Flutter

FastAPI | NodeJS | ExpressJS | Android

Platforms and Tools Linux | Heroku | Google Cloud | Elasticsearch | Kibana | Shell Scripting | Docker | CI/CD | VCS

SQL and NoSQL Databases | GitHub Actions

Languages

Hindi (mother tongue), English (fluent)